what is the degree awarding Gap in
higher education a degree awarding Gap
refers to the difference between the
proportion of students from one group
awarded of first class or upper second
degree compared with another peer group
the widest gaps are between the
groupings of disabled and non-disabled
higher and lower socioeconomic and white
and black and minority ethnic students
the largest awarding gap currently
exists between black and white student
peers even when a student's age gender
socioeconomic status and entry
qualifications are similar the degree
awarding Gap still exists making this a
concern for
institutions in England the office for
students part of the department for
Education states that the differences in
degree award outcomes may be the
consequence of a lack of diverse
environment and a non-inclusive care
culum degree awarding gaps become more
pronounced if students belong to more
than one category like being a woman
from a low socioeconomic background and
being from an ethnic
minority this is the impact of
intersectionality historically
universities have adopted what is known
as a student deficit model blaming the
individual for academic weakness or
perhaps choosing the wrong course this
lack of achievement was entitled The
attainment Gap the Contemporary term
awarding Gap rather than viewing the
student as deficient places the onus on
the institution to review consider and
action their policies and practices as
to why the awarding gaps
persist what are the
causes there are many complex reasons
behind the gaps between distinct groups
a higher education funding Council for
England report suggested the limitations
of teacher expectations of students as
having an impact on great outcomes
however focusing on the largest awarding
gap between white and black and minority
ethnic students some of the causes
suggested by universities UK and the
national Union of students include
institutional culture the culture of an
institution is identified as a crucial
factor in relation to the degrees
awarded to students from black Asian and
minority ethnic
backgrounds ethnic diversity among role
models and staff having small numbers of
black Asian and minority ethnic staff
has been acknowledged as limiting an
institution's capability to address the
awarding gaps curriculum content design
and
delivery the design of the curriculum
its content the way it's written and how
it's taught can have a significant
impact on the way that students from
diverse backgrounds and ethnicities
respond to their course lecturers and
tutors
belonging a strong theme in literature
is the importance of inclusion and
belonging the national Union of students
found that when black Asian and minority
ethnic students were asked why they were
less likely to be satisfied with their
experience and felt less likely to get a
first or upper second respondents
repeatedly cited feelings of discomfort
isolation and a sense of not
belonging social cultural and economic
capitals access to advice guidance and
resources and finance can depend on
whether a students parents or Guardians
have the knowledge and experience to
support them these obstacles can be made
worse by schools and colleges not
providing sufficient information or
guidance
resources how do we reduce the awarding
Gap advaned he recommends higher
education institutions should adopt a
project approach which focuses on three
key elements to close the awarding gaps
organizational
change improving institutional processes
enhancing the Knowledge and Skills of
staff and better supporting students are
important to address unequal outcomes
for students institutions can do this
through developing mentoring schemes
workshops embedding equality diversity
and inclusion in promotion criteria and
measuring the impact of contemporary
initiatives inclusive curriculum an
inclusive curriculum is one that is
student centered and allows students to
draw on their own experiences and
perspectives so that students are
leading the learning and are learning
from each other it includes multisensory
delivery strategies which expose
students to a variety of mediums that
are exciting engaging and interactive
inviting speakers from from different
cultural and social backgrounds to cover
additional aspects of the curriculum or
different perspectives also enriches the
curriculum student
support student support services are a
key area for addressing black and
minority ethnic awarding gaps there are
many examples of student support
activities student co-creation training
student partnership and mentoring
schemes student course representative
training and partnering with the Student
Union
degree awarding gaps can have a lasting
impact on people's lives families and
communities many companies and
postgraduate courses require a first
class or upper second degree for
graduate employment or study so the Gap
can limit people's life chances
opportunities and
incomes by working to close degree
awarding gaps we are creating Equitable
outcomes for all students
[Music]
get more from the open University check
out the links on screen now